<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of succession to the crown of England stated in a letter to a member of the honorable House of Commons : being an answer to that pamphlet that pretends to prove the Parliament hath no power to alter succession / by W. G., Gent.</title>
            <author>W. G., Gent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42704</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13791663</idno>
  <idno type="VID">101857</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240886934</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing G67</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11480</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13791663</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42704)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101857)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 454:34)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of succession to the crown of England stated in a letter to a member of the honorable House of Commons : being an answer to that pamphlet that pretends to prove the Parliament hath no power to alter succession / by W. G., Gent.</title>
                  <author>W. G., Gent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Parliament.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Succession --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101857:1"/>
            <p>THE CASE OF SUCCESSION TO THE CROWN OF ENGLAND STATED, In a Letter to a Member of the Honorable House of COMMONS.</p>
            <p>Being an Answer to that Pamphlet that pretends to prove the Parliament hath no Power to alter Succession.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. G.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>Printed, 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:101857:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101857:2"/>
            <head>The Case of Succession to the Crown of <hi>England</hi> Stated, in a Letter to a Member of the Honorable House of <hi>Commons.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Hope that Impudent Scurrulous <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> stuffed with Fallacious Arguments, will have no effect upon you, and the rest of our Noble <hi>Patriots,</hi> who so Religiously, and with a daring <hi>Integrity</hi> stands up for the Vindication of our Country, from <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery.</hi> As for those that are, their Sense was always so, and would be glad of any colourable Pretext, to back their Damnable Opinions, and Justifie their introducing of absolute Tyranny, under the Title of Divine Right, which consists, neither with the Law of God, nor Nature, the Two Fundamental Points our Author goes on, so as to invallidate those, all he saith falls to the Ground, which I hope I shall make appear in the following Discourse. Our Cunning <hi>Sophister</hi> begins with the Parliaments Power about Succession, Grounded on the Thirteenth of <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Chapter the First, and feign would inforce this Opinion, that it neither affected him, as he Writ to, being a Member of Parliament, because he had an Interest in the Legislative Power, nor me, speaking of himself, because not Consulted with, and this he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to prove from Presidents, wherein the Country was Consulted before the passing of any Extraordinary Act, which would be an Argument, if he could really prove, that it is always absolutely necessary to Consult them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the passing any important Bill, which he neither doth nor can, it being the constant practice to the Contrary, by reason all persons that are not in the Lords House, are in the House of Commons, partly coagmentive, and partly Representative, that is, in Person, or by Representation,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101857:3"/>
               <hi>Cookes</hi> Institutes 4<seg rend="sup">to</seg>
               <hi>Fol.</hi> 2. and so need not be Consulted, as absolutely necessary to the passing of any Bill, so much to his first reason, as to his harangue of himself, I shall pass it over and come to those Maxims, which he saith are not to be denyed, which in truth are not grantable to him in that sence he takes them.</p>
            <p>The first is, that God, Nature, and the immutable Customs of the Realm have placed things above the influence and coertion of the Power of the Three Estates, Kings, Lords, and Commons, which being meant of the Government is not to be granted for several reasons that ensue hereafter, and here he hath recourse to the Reverend Judges, as so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Delphian Oracles, or infallible expounders of the Statute Laws, which in cases doubtful, i'le admit, but not always their opinion for Law, knowing they always were, and will be influenced according to the times, but of Statutes, positive and plain, there needs no strained Exposition, as all are, that tend to this purpose.</p>
            <p>So that, our scribling Imposter disguising himself, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pleasing Character of a true Zealot for his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try at this time, the most acceptablest if he can but make these Statutes, be thought intricate, and to contain matters of greater weight, then is obvious to any indifferent Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, then comes into play their Conscientious Expositers the Judges, who, as he saith, have declared in all ages many Statutes void, without wronging their Consciences and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, it may be so, and God forbid, but that some Judges should be honest in all Ages.</p>
            <p>But then on the other hand, their hath been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bad Judges as in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, several Judges Suffered for going contrary to Law; and the like in <hi>Richard</hi> the Seconds time, for the Expounding of the Statutes, contrary to Law, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101857:3"/>yet such as these our Auhotr would have to be Presidents, if we would rely upon him, and not consider that the Law varies according to the times and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances.</p>
            <p>For all Laws took their Commencement, from the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of making those Laws, which varies almost every Kings Reign; so as to grant him his Opinion is to ensnare us, they presuming upon the Judges Favor, let the worst happen (which is to have an Act past against the Duke) in having a favorable Construction upon the Statute, to their advantage, which may be very much feared, since the Chief of them is so ready, as with a daring Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to say, that the bringing in of Popery by Blood should not be impeeded by shedding of Innocent Blood. Let the Country say what they would, and so released the Poyson Doctor, whose Crimes were as fully proved, as any that dyed before upon the same account; Thus he thinks slyly to Insinuate his Opinion under the pretence of both Law and Reason, which in it self rightly consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, carries neither. Therefore I hope our Noble Patriots are Wiser then to be Guld out of all they have, by such Fopperies.</p>
            <p>Next, I come to enter upon the Considerations, on which our Pamphletiers grounds the Parliaments disability, which are these, the Lawes of God and Nature, the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> Common and Statute, the Cannon and Civil Laws, History, Antient and Modern Records of Parliaments, and other Courts, to prove which he and his Tribe takes it <hi>pro Confesso,</hi> which none else doth, that the Crown is defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by the Laws of God, Nature, and the Succession in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>separably, and next to proxanimity of Blood, and so all Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Laws are void to the Contrary, which being denyed and made to appear to the contrary, the Statute stands in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101857:4"/>force, to clear which, we must see the nature of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and how it began.</p>
            <p>Men at the first, before they were associated in Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties had no particular Laws to be ruled by, but the Law of Nature or of Reason, which is all one which <hi>Lex Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae,</hi> leaves all things Common which is <hi>Status Belli,</hi> and gives a Man a right to what he can get, there being no publick Laws to distinguish and defend properties, and leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Man to Act as a Man, that is, according to his reason (to which end God gave it him) which is to Act that, which is good and best for himself, for reason is but a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty to use every thing suteable to it's Nature, and to make it subservient, and profitable to him.</p>
            <p>So, that being a rational understanding Creature by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whose Principal Inclination is to true Knowledge, on which both present and future happiness doth depend, his outward carriage is naturally proportionable to his inward parts, for whatsoever is to be done in a peculiar reference to any thing, is so to be done as shall be most necessary and profitable, for the obtaining of that thing, and Man considering how to make himself happy, and his Life com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, which is the effect of his Reason; and knowing he can never attain unto his desires, so long as Men lives without Laws, which should restrain the strongest from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vading the weaker. Therefore they enter into a Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate State of Society, being also enduced to it upon seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Reasons, as</p>
            <p>First, for mutual Love and Society, and also God and Nature having so Ordered Man-kind, that no one hath all things sufficient of his own, for his Necessity, but wants the help of his Neighbor, and so desireth Mutual So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, and also for Protection sake, both to his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and good, from one more Powerful and able,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101857:4"/>who may assault his Person, and invade his Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>And, since it is evident, that men are desirous to live together, upon these Considerations, yet cannot they live together quietly upon the reasons aforesaid, unless by some agreement, they chose some wise Person to arbitrate all differences, that should arise. When passion stirreth up Contention, the stronger compelling the weaker to obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and thus you see the Nature of Civil Government appear, and the Laws of Man to be established, which is for the good of them for whom it is instituted, according to which, is that of <hi>Aquina</hi>'s <hi>Lex Humana est orationis or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinati ad bonum Commune, ab eo qui curam Communitatis habet, praemulgata.</hi> As likewise, that of <hi>Horace, Sater,</hi> 3. <hi>Ipsa utilitas justi propè Mater &amp; aequi,</hi> which is that profit and Common good made Men live first together, both which appears by what hath been said; The People (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined by <hi>Cicero</hi> according as St. <hi>Austin</hi> relates, is <hi>caetus mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudinis hominum juris conscensu &amp; utilitatis Communione associatus, is pertinent</hi> to our discourse) have not only a great interest in the making of Laws, without whom, none can be made according ro this of <hi>Demosthenes,</hi> who saith, the Law is the Common ingagement of Society, that is, of a Society, or as <hi>Julian</hi> a great Lawyer in the Roman Emperors times, who saith, <hi>ipsae leges nullâ alia ex causâ nos tenent quam quod judicio populi receptae sunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From this Discourse is to be gathered this Conclusion, that the end of Civil agreements, is the Tranquility and safety of humane Society; and all Laws, that tend not to the publick good, nor preserves that right due to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monality, are unjust and void <hi>propter defectum justitiae le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galis,</hi> which always does or ought to intend the publick good.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:101857:5"/>
            <p> So that, here you see, that Monarchy is far from being <hi>de Jure Divino,</hi> or by the Law of Nature, but ariseth by consent; so that the succession is transferable, when the publick safety requires it, and so all Statutes tending to that publick safety are good, being grounded on the ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate end of all Laws, and Civil Government, which is common safety: Yet if we had no Law for the Succession, as we have Laws, <hi>Aristotle</hi> saith, that Laws ought to be accommodated to the times and Customs, and if one change, the other to be changed with them, unless a greater damage come by the new then by the old.</p>
            <p>If Monarchy is by election and agreement, then it is neither <hi>de Jure Divino</hi> nor <hi>de Lege Naturali</hi> but it is by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection and agreement, as hath been shewed; <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Conclusion is clear enough: And again, if the Law of Nature Commands Common safety, then it allows the means to attain to it, but it Commands Common safety, <hi>Ergo</hi> the means are allowed. And the means and way to preserve the Common good and safety is by Parliaments. So that you see by the Law of God and Nature, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament may determine things in dangerous cases, against the power of which, that is, of Parliaments demanding or enacting that, which tends to the publick safety; no Statute nor Custome can prevail, but is void and unjust, as being against the Law of Nature it self. <hi>Doct. &amp; Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place, let us see, what inconvenience will happen according to his Doctrine. Our <hi>Magna Charta</hi> is of no force, and all the Laws are but as so many Rules a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst our selves, but while the King pleases, it cannot be kept within any bounds, but throws off this well Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted Government, and brings in absolute Tyranny, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Power to invade any mans Life and property at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101857:5"/>if this be agreeable to reason or to the end of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, let all men Judge. But I hope the Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will never be tryed here, whether it is or no; And further it is against the Law of Nature, that Succession is inseparably incident to the next of Blood; for if no safety can be expected from the Successor, as may oftentimes happen; as when the Person is incapable of Government, in either being a natural, that is not fit at all to Govern himself, cannot be thought fit to Rule the Common-wealth; or else one, who minds his own profit more than the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks: For Civil Government was instituted, primarily, for the publick good, which was the ends of its institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and but secondarily to the profit of him, to whom the care of administration was committed.</p>
            <p>And therefore when these two happen, they are want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to themselves, if they do not seek there own good and safety; for what hath nature endued us with reason, but to seek our own safety. Therefore, if we do not, it is the ready way to run into absolute ruin, and destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which both the Laws of God, Nature and Man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth to the contrary, which is evident by the more particular Laws, according to Times, Places, and Customs, drawn from the General Principles of the Law of God and Nature, only to point out a way of Happiness to Man, all which, would be alterable at the will of the Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor, according as he is good or bad, but these Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing, but what is morally good are unalterable, by all which it appears, the Imperial Crown is not <hi>de Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Divino,</hi> nor, that it is unseparably incident to proximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but is alterable when necessity requires. For no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy will deny.</p>
            <p>But that it shall lineally descend, when the safety of the State enforceth not to the contrary. It much behov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our Author to make good, what he saith to prove,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101857:6"/>that he from whom our present King claims, and is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended from, had it <hi>de Jure Divino,</hi> as for the <hi>Britains,</hi> who were the true Kings of this Island, and by <hi>Caesar</hi> in his Commentaries thought to be <hi>Indig<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nae</hi> except the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, which might be peopled and take there manners and customs from the Gaules; what their Government was is not clearly made out, when <hi>Caesar</hi> came but after the Romans left this Island, from <hi>Lucius</hi> being then King, at the Romans departure to the time of <hi>Cadwallador,</hi> who was the last of the Brittish Blood, the <hi>Britains</hi> lost all by degrees to the <hi>Saexons,</hi> whom, I hope, none will conclude came in by Divine right. For then Conquest is by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right, and then I am sure a great many absurdities will follow.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Saxons</hi> Warr'd amongst one another, till <hi>Egbert</hi> the 18th King of the <hi>West-Saxons,</hi> got the whole Kingdom, and named it, <hi>England,</hi> whose descendents Married with no British Heirs, or that was likely to be Heirs; for <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelbold, Ethelwolphs</hi> Son, took his Fathers Widow <hi>Judith</hi> to Wife, but had no Issue by her, and dyed; and she was afterwards Married to the Earl of <hi>Flanders,</hi> from whom after many descents, came <hi>Maude</hi> Wife to <hi>William</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror; from whom our Kings are descended.</p>
            <p>Next comes <hi>Ethelbert Ethelbolds</hi> Brother, and Reigned a while, and dyed without Issue; next to him succeeded his Brother <hi>Ethelred,</hi> who dyed also Issueless; to whom suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded his Brother <hi>Alfred;</hi> to him succeeded his Son <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> Surnamed the <hi>Elder,</hi> who hath Three Wifes, by which he had Six Sons, whereof Three of them dyed, and the Eldest Son by Name <hi>Alhelston</hi> succeeded his Father, who dyed unmarried; to whom succeeded his Brother <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund,</hi> who dyed and left two Sons, <hi>Edwyn</hi> and <hi>Edgar; Edwyn</hi> succeeded and dyed without Issue, to him succeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101857:6"/>his Brother <hi>Edgar,</hi> who had a Bastard, named <hi>Edward,</hi> that succeeded him, who dyed without Issue; and another Son called <hi>Ethelred,</hi> who came to the Crown by the death of his Brother, Killed by his Mother <hi>Elfrida,</hi> he Married Two Wifes, by the first he had <hi>Edmund,</hi> and by the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, who was <hi>Emma,</hi> Sister to the Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> he had <hi>Edward</hi> and <hi>Alfred, Edmund</hi> succeeded his Father, and had two Sons <hi>Edward</hi> called the outlaw and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, this Son <hi>Edward</hi> Married the Emperor <hi>Henry</hi> the second Daughter, by whom he had <hi>Edgar Ethling</hi> the right Heir to the Crown, though he never had it, from whom our present King claims, and according to our Pamphleteer, joyns the <hi>Brittish, Saxons, Normands,</hi> and <hi>Scottish</hi> Blood.</p>
            <p>Which to the Three last doth fully appear, but to the first it is not clear, if at all, because the <hi>Brittish</hi> Blood Royal ended in <hi>Cadwallader,</hi> as History plainly shews, and it doth not appear that the <hi>Saxons</hi> Married with any of the Blood Royal, that could give them a title more pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful, then that of their Sword, so that the <hi>Saxons</hi> came in by Conquest, which is not <hi>de Jure Divino,</hi> and <hi>Edgar Ethlyn</hi> was a <hi>Saxon,</hi> from whom our King claims: And therefore claims by descent, according to the Constituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Government and no otherwise.</p>
            <p>In the next place it is evident by Scripture, that Proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity is not always inseparably incident to Succession; for <hi>Jacob</hi> past over <hi>Reuben, Simeon,</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> and placed the Scepter on <hi>Judah,</hi> and it was so far from displeasing of God, that to shew it was not displeasing to him, he Confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10. <hi>The Scepter shall not be taken from</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, <hi>nor a Law giver from his Thigh,</hi> which is a Prophesie of a future Royal dignity of that Tribe; where you may observe that priority and proximity was not Material, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not observed in laying a Foundation of a future Royal
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101857:7"/>Government, and several other remarkable instances; as of <hi>David, Solomon,</hi> who came to the Crown by a promise made by <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Bathsheba,</hi> who was before his Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine; and <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> and <hi>Jehu</hi> which our Pamphleteer would fain avoid, by saying, that the Law and not the Example is to be followed.</p>
            <p>Gods will is a Law to us, and therefore by following his Examples we obey his Laws, and therefore these be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Acts of his will, we ought to follow, as being grounded upon that, which is the Eternal Law, that is, Gods will. These Princes were not made Examples of, till many and great transgressions, neither doth this intend any other, then when serious and weighty Considerations debarrs the Succession, else not: And you may see it was too pinching for him, which made him pass it over so slightly, by endeavoring to salve it with such a reason, as makes the Examples the more Valuable upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and renders them above Disputation. Those Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors he quotes, as St. <hi>Jerome</hi> and St. <hi>Chrysostom</hi> are only in the affirmative, that proximity and priority is prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in common cases, which none will deny, but not negatively (which must prove what he intends) that when the safety of the Nation is in danger, that they are not waiveable, for that would be a slat contradiction of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, if that was their Opinion, as he cites them for. And then I may say whether it is better to believe God or Man; for the Example in the Scripture are to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and as for <hi>Bodine</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Lawyer, the practice of his own Country confutes his Opinion, by reason of the Salique Law, which is a most unjust Law, as not agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Law of God, and but a pretence to justifie the Title of an Usurper.</p>
            <p>And moreover, must these Men give Laws of Successi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101857:7"/>to Princes, when God himself never did, neither to his own People the <hi>Israelites,</hi> nor to the other Nations of the World, by all which it appears, that the Three Estates of the Kingdom, <hi>viz.</hi> King, Lords, and Commons, may dispose of the Succession, for the safety of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that being the end of Civil Government. And that the Imperial Crown of <hi>England,</hi> is due only to the present possessor, by descent and Birth-right Confirmed by seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Acts of Parliament; and not by Divine right; an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion exploded not only as false and dangerous, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing that Act of King <hi>James,</hi> which in its self can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not oblige against the Common safety, and obliges no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then agrees with publick good and general safety, and not to be esteemed of by any, but those who are admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of Slavery, and who, by my consent, were it not Communicable, should be the first now to feel its Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects.</p>
            <p>The next thing he goes upon, is the fidelity due to the Prince, which is adjudged by the Lord Chancellor, and the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in <hi>Calvins</hi> case, the 6th <hi>Jacob</hi>'s, to be due by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable Law of Nature, with fidelity, according to the premised Original of Government, is due by nature to the Prince; so long, as he lives and intends the publick good, but when he declines from that, Querie, for then I am bound patiently to let him Cut my Throat, if he will, which is <hi>repugnant</hi> to the Law of Nature, which Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands my <hi>preservation,</hi> which perhaps was the reason, why the Barons in King <hi>Johns</hi> time took up Arms for their liberties, but this point being a greater <hi>Noli me Tangere,</hi> Then the Succession <hi>de Jure Divino,</hi> which may make People loose in their Allegiance.</p>
            <p>I shall say no more of at this time, and as to the Statutes 24. <hi>Henry</hi> 6th. Chap. 12.34. <hi>Henry</hi> 8. Chap. 1.23 of <hi>Eliz.</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:101857:8"/>Chap. 1. which he would being to prove natural Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Allegiance, is to be understood of those that are born in the Kingdom, and of the King in his Natural Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, and not politick; and in no other sence it is to be taken; for man by Nature could not have such a power, and exact such an Obedience from another, as is due from a Subject to his Prince. Therefore you see, what Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces our Author uses to wrest the sence of things, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise then what they are, or can naturally bear, on purpose to entrap the Vulgar.</p>
            <p>All those Statutes and Cases, which are Cited to prove the King of <hi>England's</hi> Title to the Crown, to be by inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Birth-right, and by descent and priority to take place might be spar'd; for none contradicts them, if no urgent necessity compells to the Contrary: As where the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Law of the Nation is broken, as when there can be no safety, but general Ruin and Destruction expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from the next Successor; therefore no Statute Law can oblige to the contrary, but leaves a power in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to remedy it, and succession, so far as it goes along with the general safety, is a Fundamental Law and no otherwise.</p>
            <p>Next he comes to take notice of the mutual attainders between <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaster,</hi> and that by gaining the Crown each ceaseth. To which I answer, if several descents both from the <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>Normans,</hi> for their Successions were often interrupted, as appears in History, gives a legal Title to those that claim along time after, which is the ground of our Kings Claim; why might not several descents Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate a Title to them of the House of <hi>Lancaster;</hi> for their Title was as well grounded as the <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>Normans,</hi> and if their descent shall not Create a title to them, it could not to the <hi>Saxon</hi> and <hi>Normons;</hi> for <hi>Quod initio
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101857:8"/>non valet id tractu temporis non convalescit,</hi> and here are several descents in both; but you may say there is more in one then in the other, but that availeth little, for what is not good at first cannot be good afterwards, unless by Authority of Parliament; which shews how necessary it is, for the King in Possession to be backt by the Parliament, and that it is the Power the King and Parliament hath, takes away the Attainder more then the force of the Law; because there is no Power to put it in Execution, and Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution is the life of the Law.</p>
            <p>The last thing he falls on, is the Statute of 13. <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> which was the strongest Argument he had to grapple with, as in truth appears by his so weakly arguing against it, and relates the affairs of those times, which were the occasion of that Statute; from whence he would fain urge that it was intended against <hi>Scotland</hi> only, which could not be, for she declared him Successor on her Death-bed, and if it had been intended in particular against King <hi>James,</hi> the Parliament would not so willingly have accepted him for their Prince, and that Statute stand still unrepealed; but it was in general, to reserve a Power in the Parliament, to settle the Succession for the greatest advantage of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when the necessity of it doth so require. Thus I hope I have given you satisfaction in this concern, and should be glad if you received the Contentment, as I wish you,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours <hi>W. G.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>